Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series XXIX: Independent and Unidentified Footage, 1980-2014; 479079
  - Labrandero, Daniel - Event footage, undated; 467685 (Box 91, Cassette ref368, Box 80, Dvd ref368)
    Daniel Labrandero was born in Spain and was a former Loyalist who fought against Franco in the Spanish Civil War. He subsequently was killed in Cuba in the fighting against Batista.
    Fidel speaks at a commemoration attended by Cuban veterans of the Spanish Civil War.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:21:48.
  - "Madre de Tato", undated; 479682 (Box 59, Cassette ref1339)
  - Mandela, Nelson, undated; 479661 (Box 65, Cassette ref1318)
    This film contains newsreel footage, most likely of Nelson Mandela in Cuba.
  - Mandela, Nelson: Footage of inauguration (Fidel Castro attends), 1994; 467300 (Box 94, Cassette ref753, Box 83, Dvd ref753)
    This footage includes much of Nelson Mandela's inauguration, including arrival of dignitaries such as Al and Tipper Gore, Jesse Jackson, and Fidel Castro. The footage shows Mandela taking an oath and several speeches related to the inauguration. At the very end there is a brief clip of a ball game and a news clip from Lima.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:01:00
  - Mandela news clips, release from prison, 1990 February; 467218 (Box 94, Cassette ref835, Box 83, Dvd ref835)
    Contains news clips from CNN, ABC, and several other news sources. They mostly relate to Nelson Mandela's release from prison. This video contains duplicated content from other videos.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:50:54.
  - "Mandela Parlamento", undated; 467296 (Box 42, Cassette ref757, Box 83, Dvd ref757)
    This brief footage appears to concern the Mandela government in South Africa. There is a press conference in Cape Town and off-air recordings from Cuban TV. The sound is inconsistent.
  - "McNamara Speaks, Jorge Risquet, Wayne Smith", undated; 467248 (Box 39, Cassette ref805)
  - "Mexico (Mex 1)", undated; 479672 (Box 67, Cassette ref1329)
    This video contains footage of the aftermath of an earthquake in Mexico. Footage does not appear in any of Bravo's released films to date.
  - "Mexico (Mex 4)", undated; 479671 (Box 59, Cassette ref1328)
  - "Miami-Havana - English; Flotilla - English", undated; 479703 (Box 66, Cassette ref1356)
    This video may contain footage from both Miami-Havana and Flotilla to Cuba.
  - Prestes, Luis Carlos: Interview, undated; 467287 (Box 94, Cassette ref766, Box 83, Dvd ref766)
    Luis Carlos Prestes (1898-1990) was a Brazilian revolutionary. He led rebels on a three-year trek (beginning in 1924) through the interior of Brazil in an attempt to spark a rebellion in the countryside. The attempt failed, but he became a romantic figure in Brazil and went on to lead the Brazilian Communist Party. He was imprisoned after a 1935 uprising, but released after World War II, and served for a short time as a senator.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:21:29.
  - Prestes, Luis Carlos: Interview (brief) and Brazil footage, undated; 467284 (Box 5, Cassette ref769, Box 83, Dvd ref769)
    This tape includes footage shot in Brazil, including a short clip of Estela Bravo interviewing Luis Carlos Prestes. The picture quality is poor and there is a constant hum that interferes with the sound. It is, however, viewable and understandable.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:05:00.
  - Rosenberg Children, undated; cuid404; 479693 (Box 59, Cassette ref1350, Box 98, Dvd ref1350)
    This video begins with an interview Estela Bravo recorded with the sons of Julius and Ethel Rosenberg, Michael and Robert Meeropol and their families. The footage was recorded in Springfield, MA on the 25th anniversary of the Rosenberg's death for a Cuban television program. Bravo asks the Meeropols about their travel to Cuba and their impressions of the country. Much of the video on this recording is in poor condition, and in many places only the audio is available. The children of Michael and Robert Meeropol discuss their visit to Cuba and describe their understanding of how their grandparents died. At the end of the segment the family sings the Cuban folk song "Guantanamera." Beginning at minute 12:00 the video changes to various clips from Cuban television programs. Many of these clips contain no audio. The second half of the video features a boxing match.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:54:26.
  - Rosenberg Case, undated; 479695 (Box 60, Cassette ref1352, Box 98, Dvd ref1352)
    This video features a television program on the execution of Julius and Ethel Rosenberg. It begins with a brief interview with their sons Robert and Michael Meeropol who talk about their parents and the loss they still feel many years after their deaths. The program, which initially aired in 1974, details the legal efforts to grant the Rosenbergs clemency or a stay of execution. The program then provides an update, recorded in 1978, which reviews government documents and questions the impartiality of judge Kaufman, who sentenced the Rosenbergs to death.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:28:48.
  - Theodrakis, Mikis: Interview, undated; 467297 (Box 42, Cassette ref756)
    Mikis Theodrakis is a famous Greek composer and supporter of Cuba/Castro. He has been a member of the Greek parliament and a government minister, as well as a spokesman for left-liberal causes and against repressive Greek regimes. This interview is not associated with one of Bravo's documentaries.
  - Various clips: "Mandela", undated; 467399 (Box 93, Cassette ref654, Box 83, Dvd ref654)
    The footage is varied, beginning with some clips from Nelson Mandela's inauguration along with some associated news coverage. This is followed by an interview fragment with an unidentified interviewee. Starting at 00:08:30 the video focuses on an American group being recognized as part of the Friendshipment program. It includes a speech by a Cuban dignitary, and then the awarding of medals to each of the Americans.
  - "Cuban terrorists Santana", undated; 479694 (Box 59, Cassette ref1351)
  - Noticias 23: Orlando Bosch Sells Lemons, and Crowd Destroys Veronica Castro's Star, undated; 479408 (Box 47, Cassette ref1069, Box 98, Dvd ref1069)
    This video features two short segments from the Miami news program Noticias 23. The first features Cuban counter-revolutionary Orlando Bosch selling lemons to supporters in the Miami area. The second features a 1991 report on the destruction of Mexican actress Veronica Castro's star on the Calle Ocho "Walk of Fame" after residents of Miami protested her visit to Cuba.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:04:36.
- Series XXX: Collected Ephemera and Publications, 1968-2014; 590731
  This series consists of an assortment of ephemera, clippings, and published materials collected by Estela and Ernesto Bravo. Clippings include copies of articles about Estela Bravo's films, interviews, reviews, and biographical articles about her career as a filmmaker. A large portion of this series consists of programs for conferences and documentary film festivals. Bravo's films were shown at many of these festivals but not all. The series also contains several playbills from dance and theatrical performances attended by the Bravos. Playbills do not relate to filmmaking, but rather reflect the artistic interests of the Bravos. Additionally, the series contains copies of the documentaries Porque Moncada? and Manos a la Obra. These documentaries were not created by Estela Bravo, but they address topics similar to those featured in her films.
  - Camp Kinderland 90th Anniversary Program, 2014 October; 592990 (Box 72, Folder 27)
  - Clippings and Ephemera About the Career of Estela Bravo, 1985-2014; 592991 (Box 72, Folder 28)
  - Documentary: Manos a la Obra, undated; 2016.025; 593079 (Reel ref2174)
  - Documentary: Porque Moncada?, undated; 2016.025; 593080 (Reel ref2175)
  - Estela Bravo: Tal Como Es/The Way She Is, 1992; 590747 (Box 72, Folder 29)
  - Federation of Cuban Women Pamphlet, undated; 590734 (Box 72, Folder 30)
  - Global Peace Film Festival Program, 2013 September 17-22; 592992 (Box 72, Folder 31)
  - Informatica Conference Program, 1990; 590735 (Box 72, Folder 32)
  - Lenin Poster (Alfredo Rostgaard), 1970; 590736 (Box 72, Folder 33)
  - Pedogagica Conferences, 1986, 1990; 590737 (Box 72, Folder 34)
  - Playbills and Programs: Dance, 1968-1969; 590738 (Box 72, Folder 35)
  - Playbills and Programs: Galleries and Libraries, 1968-1984; 590739 (Box 72, Folder 36)
  - Playbills and Programs: Music and Theater, 1968-1969; 590740 (Box 72, Folder 37)
  - Promotional DVD: Picture Your Next Shoot in Rochester NY, undated; 592994 (Box 73, Dvd 17)
  - Urbanworld Film Festival Program, 2001 August 1-5; 592995 (Box 72, Folder 38)
  - Varadero Tourism Pamphlet, circa 1960-1969; 590754 (Box 72, Folder 39)
  - Workers Unite Film Festival Program, 2014 May 9-19; 592996 (Box 72, Folder 40)
- Series XXXI: Estela and Ernesto Bravo Family Films, 1953-1969; 592997
  This series contains a small collection of family films recorded by Estela Bravo between the 1950s and 1960s. Reels contain footage of events including parties, vacations, and visits with family. They feature the Bravos during the early years of their marriage and include footage of personal moments with their children and friends. The home movies were shot in a number of locations including New York, Miami, Paris, and São Paulo. A set of reels in this series were numbered 1-7; these numbers were created by Estela and Ernesto Bravo. Several reels were accompanied with limited contextual information and have yet to be identified. Family films that are in digital formats contain similar content as several of the reels, and many have been modified to contain sound. Several videos have been overlaid with music, while others contain audio of Estela Bravo explaining events captured in the films. Contents of these videos largely document the travels of the Bravos in the 1950s.
  - 1. Transfer, undated; 593003 (Box 74, Reel ref2116)
  - 2. Despedida, undated; 593007 (Box 74, Reel ref2120)
  - 3. Festival, undated; 593006 (Box 74, Reel ref2119)
  - 4. Paris, undated; 593000 (Box 74, Reel ref2113)
  - 5. [Unlabeled Reel], undated; 593004 (Box 74, Reel ref2117)
  - 6. São Paulo, undated; 593005 (Box 74, Reel ref2118)
  - 7. Blakiin, undated; 593002 (Box 74, Reel ref2115)
  - Argentinian Parade in Paris, 1953; TW_TAM_616_ER_15 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_15)
  - Auschwitz Nazi Concentration Camp, 1953; TW_TAM_616_ER_16 (Box Electronic Records, Item TW_TAM_616_ER_16)
  - Bravos Honeymoon, 1956; TW_TAM_616_ER_17 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_17)
  - Bravos Leaving New York, 1955; TW_TAM_616_ER_18 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_18)
  - Bravo at the White House, 1953; TW_TAM_616_ER_19 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_19)
  - Bravo in Paris, 1953; TW_TAM_616_ER_20 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_20)
  - Bravo in Poland: World Student Congress, 1953; TW_TAM_616_ER_21 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_21)
  - Bravo in São Paulo Brazil at Student Conference, 1954; TW_TAM_616_ER_22 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_22)
  - Bravo in Warsaw, 1953; TW_TAM_616_ER_23 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_23)
  - Family in Argentina, 1956; TW_TAM_616_ER_24 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_24)
  - Festival de la Juventud, 1953; TW_TAM_616_ER_25 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_25)
  - Leaving by Boat New York to France, 1953; TW_TAM_616_ER_26 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_26)
  - Long Beach - Lindell & Ocean, Este & Ernesto Visit, 1958 June; 592999; 2 Reels (Box 74, Reel ref2112_01, Reel ref2112_02)
  - Meeting with Koreans, 1953; TW_TAM_616_ER_27 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_27)
  - Que Quien, 1954; 593008 (Box 74, Reel ref2121)
  - Statue de Liberty; Marvin Leiner, 1969 May; 592998; 2 Reels (Box 74, Reel ref2111_01, Reel 2111_02)
  - Unidentified - Illegible, undated; 593001 (Box 74, Reel ref2114)
- Series XXXII: Gema de Cuba, 2017
  This series contains one electronic file of the complete documentary Gema de Cuba. The 2017 documentary recounts the experience of Gerardo Hernández and his wife Adriana Perez who attempted to conceive a child while Hernández was serving two consecutive life sentences in the United States for espionage. Hernández, along with four other Cuban agents, was arrested in Miami in 1998 for spying on the United States, they became known as the Cuban Five. The Cuban government claimed they were spying on anti-Cuban terrorists in Miami, but the five were ultimately convicted of espionage and acting as foreign agents. In 2014 as US-Cuban relations began to thaw the United States government helped Hernández and Perez conceive a child through artificial insemination. Hernández and two other Cuban agents were released that year in exchange for several American prisoners in Cuba. Hernández returned to Cuba two months before the birth of his daughter, Gema.